Guide to the McNish family papers, 1773-1926.
McNish family papers, 1773-1926.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
McNish family papers, 1773-1926.
754
McNish family.
2.1 cubic ft.
Land accounts, deeds, wills, merchandising statements, school records, correspondence, recipes, contracts, bills, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Families papers from Washington County, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Miscellaneous material from Salem, Washington County, N.Y. includes papers (1774-1810) of Alexander McNish, constable, assessor, and later coroner of Salem; enumerations of real and personal property of early settlers; land accounts; deeds; wills; merchandising statements; early school records; letters from relatives in Aughentober, Northern Ireland, discussing the high price for land and consequent emigration to America, reaction to American complaints against abuse of neutral rights, and offering indentures in return for transportation; a letter (1808) from a Representative in Congress on the embargo; recipes; contracts, bills of costs, trustee accounts, and other papers (1811-1813) relating to the building of Washington Academy; diaries of Darley McNish (1888-1891); and correspondence of Darley and Sarah McNish (1874-1926).
Additional papers of Alexander McNish include correspondence and legal papers, chiefly concerned with the payment of rents and sale or leasing of lands in the Salem area, merino sheep raising, tax and debt collection, and inquests and other duties McNish performed as constable, coroner, and U.S. mail contractor. Also, letters dealing with politics and family matters, the latter including several from relatives in Ireland and in Ohio and Kentucky. Farm labor and produce accounts, fragmentary diary entries, and weather records of William McNish (1 vol., 1827-1853). Correspondents include W. M. Adam, William Barnes, William Boyd, John Doty, Eliakim Elmore, John Kerr, R. J. Meigs, Samuel Prince, W. Raleigh, Edward Savage, John Savage, Alexander Steele, James Steele, James S. Stewart, William Story, David Thomas, John Williams, and David Woods.
See Accession Folder for more detailed descriptions of contents.
SUBJECTS
Names:
McNish family.; Adam, W. M.; Barnes, William.; Boyd, William.; Doty, John.; Elmore, Eliakim.; Kerr, John.; McNish, Alexander.; McNish, Darley.; McNish, Sarah.; McNish, William.; Meigs, Return Jonathan.; Prince, Samuel.; Raleigh, W.; Savage, Edward.; Savage, John.; Steele, Alexander.; Stewart, James S.; Story, William.; Williams, John, 1752-1806.; Washington Academy (Salem, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Real property--New York (State)--Washington County; Family--New York (State)--Washington County.; Education, Secondary--New York (State)--Washington County.; Immigration--New York (State)--Washington County.; Emigration--Northern Ireland.; Merino sheep.; Cookery.; Coroners--New York (State)--Washington County.; Debtor and creditor--New York (State)--Washington County.; Postal service--United States.; Taxation--New York (State)--Washington County.; Weather.; Meteorology--New York (State)--Washington County--Observations.; Women's diaries.; Neutrality--United States.
Places:
Washington County (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; Northern Ireland--Economic conditions--19th century.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Account books.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a partial PDF finding aid with more detailed information about the collection.
- Fragments - ca. 1790s, mainly undated (Box 1)
- 1789 (Box 1)
- undated - late 18th c. - early 19th c. (Box 1)
- 1774-1788 (Box 1)
- 1790 (Box 1)
- 1791 (Box 1)
- 1792 (Box 1)
- 1793 (Box 1)
- 1794 (Box 1)
- 1795 (Box 1)
- 1796-1799 (Box 1)
- 1803 (Box 1)
- 1800-1802 (Box 1)
- 1804 (Box 1)
- 1805 (Box 1)
- 1806-1809 (Box 1)
- 1810-1814 (Box 2)
- 1815-1834 (Box 2)
- 1844-1875 (Box 2)
- 1876-1885 (Box 2)
- 1886-1889 (Box 2)
- 1890-1891 (Box 2)
- 1892-1895 (Box 2)
- 1896-1898 (Box 2)
- 1899-1900 (Box 2)
- 1901-1908 (Box 2)
- 1912-1926 (Box 2)
- School work (Box 2)
- undated (Box 2)
- undated (Box 2)
- Recipes (Box 3)
- Pictures and postcards - 1 identified picture of Miss Darley McNish (Box 3)
- 4 notebooks of Darley McNish with daily notes (diary), 1888-1891 (Box 3)
- 2 pocket date books of Abner Robertson, 1871-1872 (Box 3)
- 3 note books of William McNish concerning seasonal farming and weather, 1866-1868, 1868-1869, 1873-1874 (Box 3)
- 8 almanacs, 1835, 1873, 1877, 1883, 1889, 1892 (Box 3)
- 3 day diaries or work records, 1858, 1866, 1887 (Box 3)
- 2 check stub books of Darley and Sarah McNish (Box 3)
- The Directory for Family Worship, approved by the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland, Edinburgh, 1793 (Box 3)
- Early cookbook (fragment) (Box 3)
- Almanac, (fragment), 1830 (Box 3)
- Early farming book (fragment) (Box 3)
- Fragmented article concerning the advantages of growing flax in Ireland over Holland, 1735 (Box 3)
- Address by "the undersigned members of the House of Representatives to their respective constituents" against going to war with Great Britain (War of 1812), 1812 (Box 3)
- "The Christian Magazine and Presbyterian Preacher," Vol. VIII, no. 8 (complete), August 1839 (Box 3)
- 1773-1792 (Box 4)
- 1793-1802 (Box 4)
- 1804-1808 (Box 4)
- 1810-1811 (Box 4)
- 1812-1814 (Box 4)
- 1815-October 1816 (Box 4)
- December 1816-September 1817 (Box 4)
- October 1817-1819 (Box 4)
- 1820-April 1821 (Box 4)
- August 1821-October 1823 (Box 4)
- November 1823-November 1824 (Box 4)
- 1825-1833 (Box 4)
- Illegible dates or undated (Box 4)
- The Washington Academy in Salem, in the County of Washington, New York, 1915 (Box 4)
- 1792-1834 (Box 5)
- 1835-1857, n.d. (Box 5)
- Papers from McNish account book (Box 5)
- Account book of William McNish (Box 5)